consciousness studies is a very
interesting journey and
[Music]
part of the outcome is something that
happened to me this morning I woke up
threw away my previous speech and penned
what came to me in the middle of the
night begin at the beginning the King
said very greatly there's no better
place to begin the word commence means
to begin so here we are at the beginning
it really has taken some time for us to
get here Charles
our academic coordinator likes to say
that unlike the goal of the learning and
thinking program in consciousness
studies we get on with the unlearning
and the unthinking of things hence it
seems very appropriate that at the end
of things we find ourselves here just
right at the beginning I was wondering
if we were to walk out of this
auditorium and sit down with a palm
reader or soothsayer our fortune teller
right now before our lives got too
settled in a new rut perhaps there would
be no past for her to see and so no
future for her to tell nothing left
would be carved in the stone of our
memories and everything would be
possible everything should be possible
from here in my work we have a phrase
starting position we ask people to throw
away all their preconceived agreements
about roles and rules and path
dependencies and basically to think
about their governance as a starting
starting position that's the phrase we
use it means that whenever you find
yourself wherever you are you're there
you're here just in the right place at
your starting position
well we my friends Charles and Bharti
and Dave and Brian we are consciousness
studies graduates so I could have said
all that in a fancier way I could have
told you about process philosophy and
explained why there are more potentials
in the past than in the future although
the future potentials are infinite they
are not exhaustible I could have derived
from this cosmological asymmetry why
this means there are more actuals to be
realized in the future than could have
ever been realized in the past
despite this negative correlation with
potentials remember the elephants I
would say there will never be a time
when there were never any of them which
only means there will never be a time
when there was never a you or a me and
that makes a difference
it's a really big deal each one of us is
a unique part of this starting position
here on planet Earth in a galaxy that
embraces all we can see and echoes all
we say remind me again this moment is a
time unlike any other this moment - well
I am really not much for formalities or
pageantry like this commencement
ceremony but I confess to holding a few
little rituals out at the farm where I
live
for example I walk the dogs to the
mailbox every day at 1:30 and when I do
I sing who wants to go to the mailbox
it's my dogs version of pomp and
circumstance
perhaps walking to the mailbox is not
their goal the mailbox is not really
their thing it's the walking the
camaraderie the chance to be together
the chance to be a we we talked about
this just this past week with an
incoming cohort in consciousness studies
the question posed the question I would
put forth today is how big is your we
how big is our we occasionally in the
late spring the juvenile birds get lost
in my barn they think the only way out
is where the light shines through those
closed windows are not the way out it's
toward the lower dark barn entry that
they must go that's an allegory that
seems relevant to me today that and the
idea that it's not that in the idea that
it's only on the inside that the birds
are lost and confused
outside in the big wide world in open
sky they know where they are my friend
likes to say when you are lost in the
forest the forest knows where you are
[Music]
there's a lot of connections you could
make with this story
a girl a farm a barn a bird a forest
windows closing in the light in dark
spaces to escape through in
consciousness that
we covered them all anyway when I help
the birds out of the barn I do it with a
bit of pageantry another little ritual
like all children I carry them outside
by cupping my hands over them and they
seem to snuggle inside as if my hands
were a portable nest inside I feel there
are tiny racing hearts and sometimes I
think they are staring into my palms the
way we stare into the night sky
perplexed by things part of this little
ritual is when I release them I give
them a little boost like this and I say
here is your freedom little bird be
careful what you do with it this
graduation ceremony this speech is a
little ritual - it's our little boost
before we launch into our freedom our
new starting position we finally get to
begin again not at the ending but here
at this commencement begin at the
beginning the King said very greatly
it's the very best place to start
you